A Guide to the Tredegar Iron Works Records, 1801-1957
Library of Virginia
Included in some of the letterbooks are copies of agreements for orders and reports on the mineral resources of land in Botetourt County, Virginia, and Mitchell County, North Carolina (see 4 November 1880-17 November 1892). Also included is correspondence regarding the sale of box cars to the United Railroads of Havana (Cuba). The letterbook, 1898 April 9 to 1901 November 23, includes correspondence and progress reports on the inspection, production, and shipment of munitions made at Petersburg Iron Works, Virginia, to the Fort Monroe Arsenal, Virginia. Most of the letters were written to Lieutenant Colonel W.A. Marye, Fort Monroe Arsenal Commander, from the inspectors at Petersburg Iron Works. Included are letterbooks from Tredegars New York offices, 1868-1875. John F. Tanner, vice president of Tredegar, ran the office from 1868 until January 1870. E.A. Wickes was then appointed head of the office until 1875, when the office was closed. After the office was closed, Tredegar still maintained agents in New York including, John Fey and C. Foote. Their letterbooks are also included. Many of these letterbooks seem to be the most fragile and are unavailable to researchers at the present time.
Included at the beginning of the subseries are three boxes of note cards containing an index to seven volumes of letter books, from March 1860 to December 1861. These cards were indexed by Burke Thompson in 1947. According to a memo by Burke Thompson (Box 861), the note cards were indexed based on the subject of Tredegars contribution during the Civil War. Topics include caissons, cannons, muskets, and projectiles sold, raw materials purchased for the manufacture of munitions, the railroad system, views of succession and the war, labor, prices, prisoners of war, Confederate bonds, and battles near Richmond. Volumes indexed include: Volume I. 12 March 1860-31 May 1860; Volume II. 31 May 1860-21 August 1860; Volume III. 15 August 1860-27 November 1860; Volume IV. 28 November 1860-16 January 1861; Volume V. 16 January 1861-1 May 1861; Volume VI. 1 May 1861-24 August 1861; and Volume VII. 24 August 1861-1 December 1861. (Note: The letterbooks 1 May 1861-24 August 1861 and 24 August 1861-1 December 1861 are very badly damaged and cannot be served).
Of note, the letterbooks, 1860-1865, are of special interest to researchers interested in the Civil War. Included are letters relating to the munitions sold, including statistics on items sold and prices, munitions sold to the U.S. government before the war, problems with purchasing and shipping raw materials during the war, furnaces owned by Tredegar, the 1863 fire at Tredegar, government contracts, list of men employed at Tredegar rolling mill suspect to the conscription act of 1863, list of men between the ages of 18 and 45 working at Tredegar in 1863, and issues relating to the draft and employment of men at Tredegar. Includes correspondence to James A. Seddon (Sec. of War), William Fontaine, John W. Mosby, Stephen R. Mallory (Sec. of Navy), Thomas O. Moore (Gov. of Louisiana), John J. Pettus (Gov. of Mississippi), John Letcher (Gov. of Virginia), along with numerous other officers.
At the end of the series are two letterbook, labeled, Special letterbook 1902 June 30-1918 December 31, and, Special letterbook 1918 December 12-1944 January 26. These letterbooks are of note because they include internal memoranda and correspondence regarding employees, board meetings, and finances of Tredegar, rather than sale of its products. Topics include loans and stocks, reminders for board meetings, taxes, accounting practices of Tredegar, contributions to the Jewish War Relief Fund and Liberty Loans, payroll accounts, changes to the rolling mills, help wanted advertising, job offers, and employee wage scales, hourly rates, raises, and bonus. Of note is letter to John Souther from Archer Anderson, regarding his father, Joseph Reid Anderson, and Tredegar during the Civil War (1910 July 29) and a letter to Senator Claude Swanson regarding the eight hour work day (1911 December 21). Also includes correspondence to U.S. Bureau of Ordnance regarding orders for munitions.
SUBSERIES 2: FOUNDRY LETTERBOOKS (1905-1942)
This subseries is housed in 4 boxes and 29 volumes on shelf and is arranged chronologically. These letterbooks contains correspondence from the foundry department regarding orders for products such as, axles, sash weights, and wheels. Included is correspondence with the U.S. Bureau of Ordnance regarding munitions produced by Tredegar. Also included are lists of employees sent to the U.S. Bureau of Ordnance, 1917-1918, requesting exemption from military duty or classification. These lists often include the employees name, race, and job title. Most of the letterbooks are indexed.
SUBSERIES 3: HORSESHOE LETTERBOOKS (1907-1942)
This subseries is housed in 6 boxes and 16 volumes on shelf and is arranged chronologically. These letterbooks contain correspondence and invoices for horseshoes made by Tredegar. Topics include prices, amount, method of shipment, and confirmation telegrams. On some of the letterbooks front and back covers is a drawing with different types of horseshoes. Most of the letterbooks are indexed.
SUBSERIES VIII: ANDERSON FAMILY PAPERS (1841-1936) (bulk 1865-1920)
The Anderson Family Papers is housed in 40 boxes and 3 volumes on shelf and is arranged into seven subseries. Subseries have been designated for Anderson family, Archer Anderson, Estate of Archer Anderson Sr., Edward R. Archer, Joseph R. Anderson, Estate of Joseph R. Anderson, and Estate of St. George M. Anderson. The series consists of accounts, account books, agreements, bills, cancelled checks, correspondence, deeds, estate accounts, insurance policies, inventories, journals, ledgers, letter books, notebooks, promissory notes, receipts, stock certificates, suit papers, and taxes.
The series was maintained in its original order, although there is much overlapping between this series and the rest of the collection. It is unknown why some deeds, insurance policies, journals, letterbooks, and ledgers were placed with the Anderson family papers. Much of the information in this series relates more to the general operations of Tredegar, rather than of a family and personal nature. Therefore researchers should check all series for pertinent information. For example, researchers should note that there are numerous agreements and deeds in Subseries 4: Estate of Joseph R. Anderson, concerning the organization and purchase of land surrounding Tredegar. There are also numerous agreements and deeds in Series I: Administrative records. See Appendix B for a complete listing of agreements and deeds found in the collection.
SUBSERIES 1: ANDERSON FAMILY (1841-1919) (bulk 1860-1898)
This subseries is housed in 4 boxes and is arranged alphabetically by folder title. The series consists of accounts, bills of sale for slaves, certificates, correspondence, journals, ledgers, legal records, minutes, promissory notes, receipts, and taxes.
The accounts include a receipt from Hollywood Cemetery Company, L.T. Christian Funeral Home, and Virginia Hospital, all of Richmond, Virginia, for the care of Mrs. John F.T. Anderson, 1897-1898. The accounts also include notes from a meeting of the stockholders, 7 January 1851, containing a distribution of shares to stockholders due for the sale of property; an account of payments due J.R. Anderson from the Monteview Mining and Manufacturing Company, 1857; and receipts for supplies purchased for the Anderson family home.
The brochures include pamphlets for Bayley & Crowell Improved turbine water wheel (Wilmington, De), 1872; P. H. & F. M. Roots Rotary blowers (Connersville, In), 1864; Gillespies Rotary hydraulic governors for water wheels (Boston, Ma), 1869; Stout, Mills & Temple (Dayton, Oh) American turbine water wheel, 1872; and Greenwood Iron works Brysons turbine turret case water wheel (Cincinnati, Oh), 1869.
Of note are bills of sale for slaves purchased by Joseph R. Anderson, 1842-1865. The bills of sale include the name of the slaves, age, owner, date, and price paid. Although it is not noted on the receipts, the slaves were most likely for work at Tredegar and not for personal use. The slaves were men, women, and children purchased from Petersburg and Richmond, Virginia.
Topics included in the correspondence, 1851-1917, pertain to various estate and land settlements in Maryland, Nebraska, and Virginia; purchases from the Navy Department; debts; letters from Gustavus V. Fox, Assistant Secretary of the Navy, extolling the capabilities of Tredegar in 1866; purchase of bonds; will of Mary Jane Anderson, 1899; and a report to the Interstate Commerce Commission, dated 1908, describing the railroad tracks at Tredegar. Correspondents include Francis Thomas, James C. Dobbin, Lewis E. Mason, Joseph R. Anderson, W.E. Dodge, Charles Marshall, Gustavus V. Fox, O.F. Moore, C.M. Miller, Archer Anderson, and L.V.T. Randolph.
The legal records contain stockholder meeting minutes, 4 April 1848, regarding the sale of Tredegar to Joseph R. Anderson; a list of balances from J. R. Anderson & Companys books, 1 January 1860, and 1 October 1861; a statement of bonds belonging to J. R. Anderson deposited in the Farmers Bank of Virginia, 1863; agreement between James River and Kanawha Company and Tredegar, for the rent charge on water use, 11 July 1853; legal opinion, 9 August 1865, regarding the purchase of land in Buchanan County, Virginia, by J. R. Anderson from Edward Valentine and the issue of the devalued Confederate money; list of Tredegar bonds belonging to J. R. Anderson, 1882; receipts, petitions, correspondence, accounts, and statements regarding the sale of Monteview Mining and Manufacturing Company (Allegany County, Virginia) from Jacob M. Kunkel to J. R. Anderson, 1859; abstracts of titles and agreements for land in Duluth, Minnesota, 1891-1897; and correspondence regarding a lawsuit over the tax paid by Tredegar, 1916-1917.
The notebooks include drawings and calculations of water wheels and turbines, and promissory notes and receipts for work done on Archer Andersons home on Franklin Street (Richmond, Va.) in 1881 by George Gibson, W.W. Wingo, and other contractors. Included are stock certificates from Iron Car Equipment Company, Mobile and Montgomery Railroad Company, Monteview Mining and Manufacturing Company, Richmond and St. Paul Land and Improvement, and the Valley Turnpike Company, among others. Also included are tax receipts for land in Duluth, Minnesota and Omaha, Nebraska, 1866-1919, and correspondence, reports, constitution and by- laws, and minutes of the United States Association of Spike Manufacturers, 1885-1899.
Also included are journals and ledgers from the various incorporations of Tredegar, including Anderson Association, Anderson Association-Bacon Syndicate Purchase, Jessup Purchase Association, and J.R. Anderson and Company, 1876-1884.
SUBSERIES 2: ARHCER ANDERSON (1860-1917)
This subseries is housed in eleven boxes and contains correspondence and letter books, 1860-1917. Topics included in the loose correspondence are debts, ongoing lawsuits and court proceedings, finances, sale of property in Virginia, membership in the Union Library Association, purchases of purebred dogs, and taxes. Correspondents include Joseph R. Anderson, George Drovin, Malcolm Bruce, Camm Patteson, Solomon Heath, John A. Gum, C.W. Chapman, E.A. Semple, Kirkwood Mitchell, and Murray McGuire.
The letterbooks, 1860-1917, contain both personal and business correspondence, and although marked, private letters of Archer Anderson, most relate to Tredegar business. Almost all of the letters are from Archer Anderson, although included are letters from Joseph R. Anderson, during the 1860-1880 period. The letterbooks are very fragile, faded, and quite difficult to read, so care must be taken when using them. The letterbook marked, 1860-1870, includes correspondence from 1860-1861 and 1867-1870, but none for the period of the Civil War, 1861-1865.
Topics of a personal matters in the letterbooks include the settlement of estates for which Anderson was executor; recommendations of jobs for friends; correspondence with lawyers regarding financial affairs; correspondence with Joseph E. Johnston regarding the Civil War, 21 June 1872; biographical information on Archer Anderson, Sr., by his grandson, Archer Anderson, 20 May 1873; correspondence with Thomas J. Munford (1831-1918) regarding a manuscript written about the Civil War, 1910; travel arrangements; donation of a section of the C.S.S. Virginia to the Confederate Museum (Richmond, Va.), 1910; correspondence with historians and researchers writing articles on Civil War generals, events, and Tredegar; correspondence and payments to stores for personal purchases; correspondence regarding his appointment by the Grand Camp of Confederate Veterans of Virginia to make a recommendation to the legislature to establish a uniform symbol of the seal of the commonwealth, 1910-1912; campaign contributions to Woodrow Wilson; correspondence regarding repairs to the family home, including issues of lighting and repavement of the roads; correspondence regarding boards he was on, for example the Central Lunatic Asylum and the committee to raise money for a statue of Robert E. Lee; and school tuitions for his children.
Business correspondence includes inquiries regarding the purchase of lumber for the manufacturing of railroad cars, 1860; list of stockholders shares, 1867; land holdings in Minnesota; relating to the depression of 1873 and Tredegars financial assets; agreements between Chesapeake and Ohio Railway and Tredegar, 1873; correspondence from Joseph R. Anderson, including correspondence with John F. Tanner, 1867 April 22, regarding the organization of Tredegar; bank loan payments; sale of Tredegar stocks and bonds; purchasing of scrap metal; letters to shareholders regarding their profits; and iron ore properties in Virginia and West Virginia.
Correspondents include James K. Campbell, William Duvall, Heros von Borcke (1835-1895), Augustus Hill Garland (1832-1899), Alexander Hamilton, E.L. Hobson, William Johnston, James L. Patton, James A. Roberts, James Robb, Joseph E. Johnston (1807-1891), Crerar, Adams & Co., John F. Winston, William Scott, John Sharp, W.W. Woodruff, J.E. Wadley, Robert L. Pierrepont, E.L. Hobson, Jubal A. Early (1816-1894), Henry Morton, Alexander J. Bondurant, and John McAverney.
SUBSERIES 3: ESTATE OF ARCHER ANDERSON, SR. (1918-1921)
This subseries consists of one folder of papers, 1918-1921, including statement of taxes, correspondence, and accounts for land in Duluth, Minnesota, and a receipt for turfing graves in Hollywood Cemetery, Richmond, Virginia.
SUBSERIES 4: EDWARD R. ARCHER (1867-1918)
This subseries is housed in two boxes and includes the private notebooks of Edward R. Archer, 1894-1918, and some loose papers, 1867-1910. The loose papers include miscellaneous letters to Joseph and Archer Anderson regarding meetings of stockholders, orders for iron bars, wheels, spikes, and axles, sale of scrap iron, and price quotes. Correspondents include the Dover Company (NY), Dickson Manufacturing Company (Pa.), Virginia and Tennessee Railroad Company (Va.), South Side and Norfolk and Petersburg Railroad Companies (Va.), Chesapeake and Ohio Railroad Company (Va.), Ohio and Mississippi Railway Company (OH), Petersburg Railroad Company (Va.), and W.S. Donnan and Company (Va.).
The notebooks, contain daily notations, 1894-1918, regarding business and family life. These notebooks are a good source for the day to day operations at Tredegar during this period, especially regarding the expansions to the water power system and maintenance of buildings at the company. The notebooks also contain information on local events in Richmond, such as new roads and buildings, politics, deaths, social events, and weather. Included are reports on driving the horse shoe factory by water power; estimates of the value of Tredegar buildings; notes on the railroad strike and riot in Richmond 1903 June; repairs and expansions to the buildings, furnaces, and water systems at Tredegar; weather observations; noting deaths of prominent Richmond citizens; important events in Richmond and surrounding counties, such as the electrocution of Floyd and Claud Allen in 1913; bids for work won by Tredegar and competitors; general notes on what mills were working and which were in repair; architectural use of iron in buildings; dividends received from Tredegar stock; fire in the spike mill in 1903; purchase of the U.S.S. Monitor Montauk for scrap metal in 1904; and local political elections. National and international events noted include the coal strike of 1902 and railroad strikes; the Panama Canal; the Chicago (Ill.) fire of 1903; trial of Standard Oil in 1911; commission of a memorial for the USS Maine; loss of the Titanic in 1912; World War I; and prohibition. Drawings are included next to some of his notations, of turbine wheels, bridge repairs, layout of the buildings, and a sketch of the Richmond Horse Show in 1902.
SUBSERIES 5: JOSEPH R. ANDERSON (1865-1892)
This subseries is housed in 7 boxes and 2 volumes and contains journals, ledgers, and letterbooks. The journals and ledgers, 1865-1892, relate mostly to Andersons private expenses, such as tolls, taxes, food, telegrams, household purchases, value of Confederate currency after the Civil War, servants salaries, stock, and land properties in Maryland, Minnesota, and Virginia. Some expenses are included relating to Tredegar, such as building repair costs, gas bills, stock payments, interest, and miscellaneous sundries. Also contained are expenses for Tredegar farm land in Goochland County, including Beaverdam, Forest, Lewis, and Pleasant Green farms. Researchers interested in journals and ledgers from Tredegar should also check Series II: General Accounts.
Includes accounts with Edward R. Archer, E.L. Hobson, John F.T. Anderson, Robert Archer, George Scott, R.W. Winston, Henry Rowland, Fannie A. Hobson, William Talley, Mary F. Goodwin, Minnesota Iron Car Company, J.R. Anderson & Co., Anderson Association, Jessup-Purchase Association, and Joseph R. Anderson and Company. Ledgers A and B are indexed, while the journals are not.
The letter books, 1867-1892, are in relatively good condition, although some have water damage and have faded. The exception is the letterbook dated 1882 June 10-1886 March 12, which is too fragile and cannot be served. As with all of the letterbooks in the collection, extra care must be taken when using the books. All of the letterbooks are indexed.
Topics include stocks and bonds, selling shares of Tredegar to investors to secure capital for the company, purchases of lumber, building of a bridge and railroad track connecting Belle Isle to the northern bank of the James River, payment of taxes, loan agreement between James River and Kanawha Company and the Dover Company, repairs to personal homes, Andersons service on the Board of Visitors for Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University (Virginia Tech), establishment of a scholarship at the University of Virginia, and a brief sketch of products and types of foundries at Tredegar, written by Anderson for a publication (1876 Sept. 3-1878 June 10, page 245-248). Also includes information on the sale and rent of land and farms, both personal and Tredegar property, including the Cloverdale and Catawba furnace properties, in Maryland, Texas, and Virginia.
Correspondents include Thomas J. Boyd, Charles Marshall, T.A. Baylor, James H. Blake, Thomas H. West, Thomas H. Ellis, John F. Winslow, Joel Parker, John F. Tanner, John Netherland, James W. Henderson, Joseph Dilworth, C.P. Huntington, R. Tomlinson, William H. Aspinwall, Nathaniel Thayer, H.D. Whitcomb, John B. Garden, William W. Patton, Alexander H. Rutherford, Charles M. Miller, Joseph Wolfolk, James H. Young, D.H. Gordon, C.M. Jordan, William A. Glasgow, Charles H. Harrison, Charles C. Dwight, Jed Hotchkiss, Claiborne Watkins, and John Fey.
SUBSERIES 6: ESTATE OF JOSEPH R. ANDERSON (1848-1930) (bulk 1892-1910)
This subseries is housed in 17 boxes and 1 volume and is arranged alphabetically by folder title. Includes account books, correspondence, contracts, checks, deeds, estate accounts, ledgers, letter books, promissory notes, receipts, vouchers, and suit papers regarding the estate of Joseph R. Anderson (1813-1892) and administered by Archer Anderson, Jr.
Of note within the collection are the agreements and deeds, 1848-1930. Included are deeds relating to the early Tredegar partnership agreements between Joseph R. Anderson, Charles Morriss, Matthew Delany, Francis Glasgow, Robert Archer, Robert S. Archer, John Tanner, and William Steptoe. Also included are contracts to supply the United States Navy with steam engines for the U.S. Steamer Roanoke, 1854, and deeds for furnaces and land in Botetourt and New Kent Counties, and Richmond, Virginia; and Maryland and Minnesota. After 1892, most of the deeds and agreements relate to the financial and contractual settlements by the heirs of the estate of Joseph R. Anderson. Many of the deeds and agreements in this subseries correlate to the Real Estate Files in Series I: General Administrative Records. Researchers should consult both series to find all related deeds. An itemized listing of agreements and deeds in Series I and Series VIII can be found in Appendix B.
The main section of the subseries is the estate accounts. The estate accounts consist of account books, inventories, promissory notes, receipts, and vouchers for the settlement and division of the estate. Included are receipts to pay off personal purchases, bank loans, and interest to the heirs of Joseph R. Anderson, and taxes and repayment of loans from Tredegar. The inventories contain an itemized listing of the disbursements of the estate of Joseph R. Anderson. The estate was divided among the five children of Joseph R. Anderson: Fannie A. Hobson, Mary Anderson Bruce, Joseph R. Anderson, Jr., John F.T. Anderson, and Archer Anderson, Jr. The correspondence and letter books, 1867-1922, concern the division of the estate of Joseph R. Anderson, and include letters between the heirs of the estate, along with correspondence among lawyers, banks, and debtors, to Archer Anderson. Jr. Also included is correspondence with E.P. Alexander, president of Duluth Banking Company, regarding property Joseph R. Anderson acquired in Duluth, Minnesota. The special summaries and suit papers relate to legal proceedings regarding the division of the estate. Included is a copy of the last will of Joseph R. Anderson; stock and bond agreements; papers relating to the lawsuit of Henry A.V. Post against The Atlantic Trust Company, the Railroad Equipment Company and the Iron Car Equipment Company, 1897; and a pamphlet entitled, Car Trusts in the United States, 1894.
SUBSERIES 7: ESTATE OF ST. GEORGE M. ANDERSON (1908-1936)
This series is housed in 1 box and arranged alphabetically by folder title. Includes bank books, checks, correspondence, insurance, receipts, and tax receipts for the estate of St. George M. Anderson (d. 1936), administered by Archer Anderson, Jr. Includes personal property, state, and real estate taxes paid by St. George M. Anderson in Henrico County, Virginia, 1908-1936; real estate and personal insurance policies; and correspondence and drawings regarding land on Three Chopt Road in Henrico County, Virginia.
Arrangement